<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY tex "TeX">
  <!ENTITY latex "LaTeX">
]>
<book id="mockgals.xml" lang="en">
<title>mockgals 0.1</title>


<!-- Use section titles in cross references, not node titles. -->
<!-- %**end of header -->





<bookinfo><legalnotice><para>This manual is for MockGals, a program to make mock astronomical
objects in a FITS image and add the appropriate noise.
</para>
<para>Copyright &#169; 2014 Mohammad Akhlaghi:
<email>akhlaghi@astr.tohoku.ac.jp</email>
</para>
<blockquote><para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or
any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover
Texts.  A copy of the license is available online at
<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html">GNU FDL webpage</ulink>.
</para></blockquote></legalnotice></bookinfo>





<para>This manual is for MockGals, a program to make mock astronomical
objects in a FITS image and add the appropriate noise.
</para>
<para>Copyright &#169; 2014 Mohammad Akhlaghi:
<email>akhlaghi@astr.tohoku.ac.jp</email>
</para>
<blockquote><para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3 or
any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
Invariant Sections, with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover
Texts.  A copy of the license is available online at
<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html">GNU FDL webpage</ulink>.
</para></blockquote>


<chapter label="" id="Top">
<title>MockGals</title>
<para>MockGals is a tool to produce mock galaxies and stars based on an
input catalog or randomly into a FITS image of any given size. It can
be used to test various detection criteria. 
</para>


















</chapter>
<chapter label="1" id="About">
<title>About</title>

<para>To get started with MockGals please please see <link linkend="Quick-start">Quick start</link>.  The
following sections in this chapter are more general discussions.
</para>
<para>In the first section we will give a short review of the way modern
science has become intertwined with software and how important it is
for scientists to have very good understanding of the software they
use.  After that your rights as the reader of this document and user of
MockGals are explained and in the end of this chapter we give a short
review of how this manual is available for your use and a short
summary of the manual.
</para>







<sect1 label="1.1" id="Good-Science">
<title>Objective/critical science and its software</title>
<para>We believe that if a software (a technique) is to be used in
scientific research, it has to be open source and transparent (with a
good manual) to be open to scrutiny. Any critical/interested user
should easily be able to follow all the steps and understand all the
fine details and assumptions. History of science shows us that no
interpretation, model or technique (software) is perfect.  There are
always inevitabley unseen faults, hidden assumptions, simplifications
and approximations in any of our constructs. It is precisely these
that will ultimately allow future generations to find/correct them and
advance our experimental and theoretical knowledge of the universe we
live in. By keeping software free and transparent for all scientists,
we can most accurately convey our experiences to users who can build
on those or find their shortcomings. Viewed more generally, this will
help critical and objective science thrive.
</para>
<para>With the progress of technology, scientific results are increasingly
becoming more and more dependent on hardware and software
techniques. Therefore obscure software is arguably the biggest
roadblock in our aim to acheive this goal and a modern scientist
cannot claim to be curious in understanding the universe and our
relation to it, what ever their specific field, without accurately
understanding the software techniques they use to quench that
curiosity.  We thus believe that the wide use of free and transparent
software is one step in a larger scheme to save the sciences...
</para>
<blockquote><attribution>Karl Popper. The logic of scientific discovery. 1959.</attribution>
<para>...from narrow specialization and from an obscurantist faith in the
expert&#8217;s special skill and in his personal knowledge and authority; a
faith that so well fits our post-rationalistic and post critical age,
proudly dedicated to the destruction of the tradition of rational
philosophy and of rational thought its self.
</para>
</blockquote>
<para>To reach this goal, namely to let the users of a software be able to
understand its intricate details at their will, a software has to be
accompanied by a good and up to date manual. The user of a software
cannot claim to understand how it works only based on the experience
they have gained by frequently using it. This kind of subjective
experience is prone to very serious mis-understandings that only help
in producing dogmas and the above mentioned &#8220;obscurationist faith in
the expert&#8217;s special skill&#8221;.  Unfortunately in the commonly used
astronomical softwares, most are either closed source or don&#8217;t have a
good manual. The scientific results that are deduced from such
software are thus not objective, because in the former case scientists
have to look at it as a black box and trust its results on faith. In
the latter, it is very hard to find enough time to understand the
programming of an open source project without a clearly written and up
to date manual explaining all the ideas behind the major functions,
data structures or objects. 
</para>
<para>It is certainly time consuming for the author of a software to make
such a manual. If personal greed is put aside and our greater common
experience is considered, that time is a time well invested. Because
through sharing of these fundamental ideas, that shape all our
scientific results, and keeping them open to criticism, we can make
them more robust and thus take better steps in our common goal to
tackle the riddles of nature.
</para>
<para>Bjarne Stroustrup (creator of the <literal>C++</literal> language) says: &#8220;Without
understanding software, you are reduced to believing in magic&#8221;.  Ken
Thomson (the designer or the Unix operating system) has said very
nicely that &#8220;I abhor a system designed for the &#8220;user&#8221; if that word
is a coded pejorative meaning &#8220;stupid and unsophisticated&#8221;.&#8221; Both
these cases naturally apply even more seriously to systems written for
scientific applications and as scientists we should be loyal to such
principles if we want to remain critical and be objective. After all,
all our data and models are produced, archived and processed using
hardware and software. We cannot and should not accept any result
through faith in the programmer who wrote that particular program we
are using to publish our papers.
</para>




</sect1>
<sect1 label="1.2" id="Your-rights">
<title>Your rights as a user of MockGals</title>

<para>MockGals is &#8220;free software&#8221;; this means that everyone is free to use
it and free to redistribute it on certain conditions. MockGals is not
in the public domain; it is copyrighted and there are restrictions on
its distribution, but these restrictions are designed to permit
everything that a good cooperating citizen would want to do.  What is
not allowed is to try to prevent others from further sharing any
version of MockGals that they might get from you.
</para>
<para>Specifically, we want to make sure that you have the right to give
away copies of the programs that relate to MockGals, that you receive
source code or else can get it if you want it, that you can change these
programs or use pieces of them in new free programs, and that you know
you can do these things.
</para>
<para>To make sure that everyone has such rights, we have to forbid you to
deprive anyone else of these rights.  For example, if you distribute
copies of the MockGals related programs, you must give the recipients
all the rights that you have.  You must make sure that they, too,
receive or can get the source code.  And you must tell them their
rights.
</para>
<para>Also, for our own protection, we must make certain that everyone finds
out that there is no warranty for the programs that relate to MockGals.
If these programs are modified by someone else and passed on, we want
their recipients to know that what they have is not what we distributed,
so that any problems introduced by others will not reflect on our
reputation.
</para>
<para>The precise conditions of the licenses for the programs currently
being distributed that relate to MockGals are found in the General
Public license<footnote><para><ulink url="https://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html">https://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html</ulink></para></footnote>
that accompany them.  This manual is covered by the GNU Free
Documentation License<footnote><para><ulink url="https://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html">https://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html</ulink></para></footnote>.
</para>
<para>The paragraphs above, in this section, belong to the GNU Texinfo manual
and are not written by us! We have just changed the name &#8220;Texinfo&#8221;
to &#8220;MockGals&#8221; because it and this manual are released under the same
licenses and it is beautifully written to inform you of your rights.
</para>




</sect1>
<sect1 label="1.3" id="Conventions-and-summary">
<title>Manual conventions and summary</title>
<para>In this manual commands to be input into the command line as normal
user begin with <command>$</command>, and for those that to be input as root
(or super-user), the command begins with <command>#</command>. Note that you
need the root password in order to execute the latter commands. The
commands finish where the special type face used to show them
finishes. Be careful not to include text puctuation marks that might
follow the inline commands, they have a different font. After typing
the commands on the command-line you have to press the <keycap>Enter</keycap> or
<keycap>Return</keycap> key on your keyboard for the command to start executing.
</para>
<para>The first chapter is a quick start, explaining the generalities of
MockGals so the user can begin using it very fast. The following
chapters give a much more detailed review of each step. 
</para>




</sect1>
<sect1 label="1.4" id="Manual-formats">
<title>Manual Formats and reading recommendations</title>
<para>This manual is available in plain text, HTML, Info, Docbook, PDF and
finally the Texinfo format. The last one is the basis for creating all
the other formats. As an initial introduction the PDF and HTML formats
might be easier to begin using MockGals, but if you would like to
understand the code while reading <link linkend="How-it-works">How it works</link>, it is much
easier to do it in the info format, where for example in Emacs, you
can have one window on the code and another on the info file.
</para>
<para>Info is a very convenient format particularly useful for software
documentation. We strongly recommend becoming familiar with it if you
are not already because it can significantly enhance your experience
in programming and in your GNU based operating systems user
experience.  Operating systems like Ubuntu, Fedora, Linux Mint,
Debian, OpenSUSE, Red Hat, CentOS or Scientific linux among many
others. Info is very trivial and made for reading manuals. It provides
facilitates to navigate easily in long manuals. To learn more about it
in any GNU/linux terminal you can run: <command>$ info info</command>. It does
a fantastic job in explaining its self in practice interactively.
</para>
<para>By default, the PDF version of this manual is prepared in the A4 paper
size (210cm by 297cm). In case you prefer a letter size (8.5in by
11in), you can simply change it by following the steps below. You must
have Texinfo and &tex; installed on your system, for an explanation
on how to install them see <link linkend="Installation">Installation</link>.
</para>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic"><listitem><para>In the downloaded source directory (lets call it <filename>SRC/</filename>), open
the <filename>SRC/doc/mockgals.texinfo</filename> Texinfo source file of this
manual.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Delete the line that says <literal>@afourpaper</literal>. It is in the first few
lines of the file.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>run <literal>$ ./run.sh</literal> in that same directory, this will re-make all
the documenation formats.
</para></listitem></orderedlist>



















</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter label="2" id="Quick-start">
<title>A Quick start</title>

<para>Once MockGals is installed, if you simply run <literal>./mockgals</literal> in the
installed directory, 45 mock galaxies and 5 stars will be randomly
positioned in a <literal>FITS</literal> image of size <inlineequation><mathphrase>200*200</mathphrase></inlineequation>.
</para>



















</chapter>
<chapter label="3" id="Introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>Making mock galaxies is very important in the process of understanding
our data. MockGals was initially made with this exact
intent. Certain astronomical targets, for example elliptical
galaxies, are very sharp in their central regions, this makes a simple
calculation of the profile in the center of each pixel unrealistic for
such cases. The main advantage of MockGals is that it
integrates the central parts of profiles until a given accuracy. It
does this without any sorting or ordering and in a very fast manner.
</para>
<para>A summary of the advantages of MockGals includes:
</para><orderedlist numeration="arabic"><listitem><para>Integration of the center of the profile.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Very efficient in CPU usage, resuling in a very fast processing.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>Written in the C programming language, which is easy to understand
and modify or contribute to by any interested user.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>[To be added] Can make profiles in any dimentions. 
</para></listitem></orderedlist>



















</chapter>
<chapter label="4" id="Installation">
<title>Installation</title>
<para>MockGals relys on only 3 packages: GSL (GNU scientific library, for
mathematical functions), FFTW (for convolution) and cfitsio (for
reading to and from FITS files).
</para>



















</chapter>
<chapter label="5" id="Configuring">
<title>Configuring MockGals</title>
<para>Currently configuration paramters into MockGals can only be
given through single letter commandline options. The options are
explained below.
</para>



















</chapter>
<chapter label="6" id="Mock-Parameters">
<title>Mock parameters</title>
<para>The parameters of the profiles you want to build into a FITS image are
fed to it though a table. In this section we will review how
MockGals reads that table and how best to prepare it.
</para>



















</chapter>
<chapter label="7" id="How-it-works">
<title>How mockgals works</title>
<para>In this section we will give a complete review on how MockGals works
and how this is implemented in its coding in order to facilitate your
reading of the code and possibly modifying it and making it better.
</para>



















</chapter>
<chapter label="" id="Manual-index">
<title>Index</title>

<index role="cp"></index>






</chapter>
</book>
